ADRIAAN LEMMENS

NLP Researcher

Leuven, Belgium

adriaan.jm.lemmens AT gmail DOT com

+32 472 69 03 80

<u>lemontheme</u>

adriaan-lemmens

@adrnlem

ABOUT ME

I've been solving problems with Natural Language Processing for over 5 years, drawing on a solid foundation in both machine learning and linguistics. I'm always learning new things, not just about NLP, and I get a real kick out of sharing what I've learned with others. If you're looking for someone who is scientifically minded, values good engineering, and can engage a (non-)technical audience - that might just be me!



SPECIALIZATIONS

SOFT SKILLS

RECENT SKILLS

Deep Learning NLP & Search Efficient Python Teaching & public speaking **Empathy** Attention to detail

Web dev & JS LLM prefix tuning Neural graph mining

EXPERIENCE

Oct 2021 **Doctoral Researcher**





- Probing LMs for latent linguistic representations that can be applied to linguistic research.
- Building an end-to-end text analytics web app for researchers in the humanities.

Jan 2021 -Jul 2021

NLP / Search Engineer

Henchman

Took ownership of Henchman's search and NLP backend, successfully delivering new features under fast-changing requirements. Mentored a junior colleague and became an Elasticsearch wizard.

Aug 2019 -Jan 2021

NLP / ML Engineer

<u>Brainiar</u>

Consulted on predominantly NLP-focused projects to deliver end-to-end applications powered by machine learning. Assignments included:

- Productized Document Al
- Predicting airport capacity issues
- Information extraction on templatic documents
- Search consultant
- Mentored interns and spoke at industry-focused events.

Aug 2017 -Aug 2019

Computational Linguist / NLP Engineer

NLP Town



6

Developed models, algorithms, and services for clients in various sectors. Assignments included...

- Automatic post-editing for machine translation
- Information extraction on healthcare documents
- Knowledge mining on user-submitted text
- Search log analysis

EDUCATION

2016 – 2017 MSc. Artificial Intelligence (MAI)

Speech & Language Technology. Four-month internship at NLP Town.

MA Formal & Computational Linguistics

Thesis: A simple pictograph-to-text translation system for cognitively disabled users. Presented at CLIN27 conference.

BA Languages & Literature

Specialization: Linguistics

KU Leuven, BE

KU Leuven, BE

KU Leuven, BE

CERTIFICATES

2019 Certified Associate in Python Programming

2006 – 2010 IGCSEs & International Baccalaureate

Python Institute

NAIS, Pudong, CN

TECH SKILLS

Natural Language Processing (NLP)	Machine Learning (ML)	
Wide range of applications \cdot Neural transfer \cdot Linguistic intuition \cdot Fast data generation & annotation \cdot Intimate knowledge of OS libraries \cdot Historical knowledge	Deep and shallow \cdot Custom architectures \cdot Mathematical intuition \cdot Data tricks \cdot Model serving \cdot Pytorch	
Software Engineering	Tooling	
Backend architectures \cdot Testing, profiling, complexity analysis \cdot OOP \cdot ML abstractions \cdot CI/CD	Git · Linux · K8s, Docker · GCP, AWS	
	Databases	
	SQLite, PostgreSQL · Elasticsearch	

Languages

Python (near-daily usage since 2015) · Javascript (since 2023) · Can translate from Go & C++.

OPEN SOURCE

2023	django_components Reusable Django components	EmilStenstrom
2021	sopredictable [WIP] Take the excitement out of model persistence.	lemontheme
2020	BentoML Model serving made easy.	BentoML
2020	trefwurd [Archived] Lemmatization rule induction with regex generation and ML	lemontheme